Guide to the Phillip Lopate Papers YCAL MSS 1083
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1963-2009 and undated; 2; 21.75 Linear Feet (44 boxes)
  - Shorter works
    - Drafts of essays, stories, and poems, complete and unfinished
      - "The Invisible Woman" article drafts and notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 301-302)
      - "The Invisible Woman" pocket memo book, undated (Box 29, Folder 303)
      - Martin Constance notepads and notepad pages, undated (Box 29, Folder 304-305)
      - Maurice Sceve translation draft by Lopate, undated (Box 29, Folder 306)
      - Personal essay candidates for essay book, undated (Box 29, Folder 307)
      - Poems, poem fragments, and bad works, undated (Box 29, Folder 308-310)
      - Religion of poetry, undated (Box 29, Folder 311)
      - Soseki Natsume essay begun but never really written, undated (Box 29, Folder 312)
      - Stories, personal essays, and diary entries, uncollected, undated (Box 29, Folder 313)
      - Warren Sonbert drafts, undated (Box 29, Folder 314)
      - "We Are Family" notes and annotated drafts, undated (Box 29, Folder 315)
      - "We Are Family" steno notebook, undated (Box 30, Folder 316)
    - Drafts of essays, stories, and poems, published and unpublished
      - General, undated (Box 30, Folder 317-321)
      - "Abraham and Sarah" drafts, notes, clippings, undated (Box 30, Folder 322)
      - "Abraham and Sarah" [memo book], undated (Box 30, Folder 323)
      - "The Countess's Tutor" drafts and notes, undated (Box 30, Folder 324-325)
      - Essays for "The Forum", "How I Settled the Big Yankee-Red Sox Playoff" and "Confessions and Self-Justifications of a Sports Fan", undated (Box 31, Folder 326)
      - "Fading into the Formica: Sketches from Daily Life" notes, poetry and prose drafts, undated (Box 31, Folder 327)
      - Father essay drafts and notes, undated (Box 31, Folder 328-329)
      - "Howl and Me" and Underground Literary Alliance correspondence, undated (Box 31, Folder 330)
      - "The Lake of Suffering", undated (Box 31, Folder 331)
      - "The Limits of Empathy", undated (Box 31, Folder 332)
      - Poem drafts notebook, undated (Box 31, Folder 333)
      - Prose, general, undated (Box 31, Folder 334)
      - Prose notes, general, undated (Box 31, Folder 335)
      - Prose notes, general, undated (Box 32, Folder 336-337)
    - Essay MSS [assorted]
      - Bachelorhood outtakes, undated (Box 32, Folder 338-340)
      - Being With Children outtakes, undated (Box 32, Folder 341)
      - Being With Children outtakes notebooks, undated (Box 32, Folder 342)
      - "The Calligrapher's Daughter" annotated drafts, undated (Box 32, Folder 343)
      - Confessions of Summer outtakes, Natalie chapter, undated (Box 32, Folder 344)
      - Confessions of Summer outtakes, Natalie chapter [notebooks], undated (Box 32, Folder 345)
      - "The Dead Father: A Remembrance of Donald Barthelme" annotated drafts, undated (Box 33, Folder 346-350)
      - "The Dead Father: A Remembrance of Donald Barthelme" [notebooks], undated (Box 33, Folder 351)
      - "Lives of the Poets" drafts and annotations, undated (Box 33, Folder 352)
      - Lisette Model annotated drafts, undated (Box 33, Folder 353-354)
      - Lisette Model [notebooks], undated (Box 34, Folder 355)
      - Manuscript notes, general, undated (Box 34, Folder 356)
      - Notes for nonfiction speech, undated (Box 34, Folder 357)
      - "Osao" annotated drafts, undated (Box 34, Folder 358)
      - "Portrait of Lisette Model" annotated draft, undated (Box 34, Folder 359)
      - "Portrait of Lisette Model" for Aperture Books, 1979 (Box 34, Folder 360)
      - "Portrait of Lisette Model" for Aperture Books, annotated and edited, 1979 (Box 34, Folder 361)
      - "Samson and Delilah" annotated drafts, undated (Box 34, Folder 362-363)
      - "Samson and Delilah" notebooks, undated (Box 35, Folder 364)
      - "Uncle Vanya" drafts and annotations, undated (Box 35, Folder 365)
      - "Uncle Vanya" [notebooks], undated (Box 35, Folder 366)
      - "Will Lahiti Transform Heidi?" annotated draft, undated (Box 35, Folder 367)
      - "The Zoroastrians Struggle to Stay Alive in America" annotated draft, undated (Box 35, Folder 368)
    - Writings on film
      - Uncategorized, general, undated (Box 35, Folder 369-370)
      - Drafts of film pieces, general, undated (Box 35, Folder 371-373)
      - Drafts of film pieces, general, undated (Box 36, Folder 374)
      - Film program notes and articles, 1960s (Box 36, Folder 375)
      - Film program notes and articles, 1970s (Box 36, Folder 376-377)
      - Film articles, 1980s (Box 36, Folder 378-380)
      - Drafts of film pieces, 1990s (Box 36, Folder 381-382)
      - Film pieces, 1990s (Box 37, Folder 383)
      - Film pieces, clippings, 1990s (Box 37, Folder 384)
      - Film pieces, publications, 1990s (Box 37, Folder 385)
      - Film pieces, 2000s (Box 37, Folder 386-388)
      - Film pieces still to be considered for an essay book, undated (Box 37, Folder 389)
      - Film pieces still to be considered for an essay book, undated (Box 38, Folder 390-392)
      - Film pieces, uncollected, undated (Box 38, Folder 393)
      - Film scraps and program ideas, undated (Box 38, Folder 394)
      - Film writings, undated (Box 38, Folder 395)
      - Film writings, notes, undated (Box 38, Folder 396)
      - Blondes, undated (Box 38, Folder 397)
      - [Memo book], undated (Box 38, Folder 398)
      - "The Legacy of John Cassavetes" article drafts, undated (Box 38, Folder 399)
      - Children's point of view in film, notes, flyers, undated (Box 38, Folder 400)
      - City essay films, undated (Box 38, Folder 401)
      - "Contempt: The Story of a Marriage" for the New York Times, drafts, clippings, undated (Box 38, Folder 402)
      - "Dumb and Dumber" piece on the movies for Katherine Washburn, anthology on the dumbing down of American culture, undated (Box 39, Folder 403)
      - Film pieces for Esquire magazine, clippings, undated (Box 39, Folder 404)
      - "Hollywood Looks at the Business Office" article drafts, undated (Box 39, Folder 405)
      - Houston Museum of Fine Arts, Film Culture no. 70-71 [photograph book], undated (Box 39, Folder 405A)
      - Houston Museum of Fine Arts program materials (clippings, brochures, articles), undated (Box 39, Folder 406-408)
      - Houston Museum of Fine Arts program notes, undated (Box 39, Folder 409)
      - Interview with Pauline Kael, undated (Box 39, Folder 410)
      - Interview with Pauline Kael news clippings, undated (Box 39, Folder 411)
      - Interview with Pauline Kael steno book, undated (Box 39, Folder 412)
      - Jane Campion Vogue article, undated (Box 40, Folder 413)
      - "L'Enfance Nue: The Fly in the Ointment" article, notes, notepad, undated (Box 40, Folder 414)
      - Materials from the International Design Conference in Aspen, undated (Box 40, Folder 415)
      - New York Times film pieces, articles, undated (Box 40, Folder 416)
      - New York Times film pieces, clippings, undated (Box 40, Folder 417-418)
      - "Novels and Films: A Comedy of Remarriage" drafts and notes, undated (Box 40, Folder 419)
      - Otar Iosseliani article drafts and notes, undated (Box 40, Folder 420)
  - Books
    - Against Joie De Vivre
      - Against Joie De Vivre copy edited typescript, undated (Box 40, Folder 421-422)
      - Against Joie De Vivre copy edited typescript, undated (Box 41, Folder 423-426)
    - American Movie Critics Anthology
      - American Movie Critics Anthology annotated draft, undated (Box 41, Folder 427-430)
      - American Movie Critics Anthology annotated draft, undated (Box 42, Folder 431-433)
      - American Movie Critics Anthology reviews and publicity, undated (Box 42, Folder 434-436)
    - Bachelorhood
      - Bachelorhood copy edited typescript, undated (Box 42, Folder 437-439)
      - Bachelorhood copy edited typescript, undated (Box 43, Folder 440-441)
    - Notes on Sontag
      - Susan Sontag research [notebook], undated (Box 43, Folder 442)
      - Notes on Sontag Ellen Foop [Princeton University Press] typescript proof, undated (Box 43, Folder 443-444)
      - Notes on Sontag Ellen Foop [Princeton University Press] edited proof, copy, undated (Box 43, Folder 445)
      - Notes on Sontag edited draft fixed by Karen, undated (Box 43, Folder 446-447)
      - Notes on Sontag edited draft fixed by Karen, undated (Box 44, Folder 448)
      - Notes on Sontag Elizabeth Kendall's copy, annotated draft, undated (Box 44, Folder 449-451)
      - Notes on Sontag Hanne Winarsky's [Princeton University Press] copy, undated (Box 44, Folder 452-454)
      - Notes on Sontag review copy, undated (Box 44, Folder 455)
      - Letter to Phillip Lopate from Princeton University Press on the publication of Notes on Sontag, undated (Box 44, Folder 456)
      - Notes on Sontag clean printed copy, undated (Box 45, Folder 457)
      - Notes on Sontag second version, undated (Box 45, Folder 458)
      - General clippings and emails, undated (Box 45, Folder 459)
      - Publicity and press for Notes on Sontag, undated (Box 45, Folder 460-464)
    - Rudy Burckhardt monograph
      - Rudy Burckhardt notes [spiral notebook], undated (Box 46, Folder 465)
      - [Two notebooks], undated (Box 46, Folder 466)
      - Interview notes with Rudy Burckhardt and "Remembering Rudy" memorial materials, undated (Box 46, Folder 467)
      - "Recent Films About Artists" by Rudy Burckhardt, undated (Box 46, Folder 468)
      - Rudy Burckhardt biographical information, filmography, clippings, undated (Box 46, Folder 469)
      - Jacob 2 edits and revisions, undated (Box 46, Folder 470-471)
      - Edith Schloss edits and revisions, undated (Box 46, Folder 472)
      - Christopher Sweet edits and revisions, undated (Box 46, Folder 473)
      - Yvonne edits and revisions, undated (Box 47, Folder 474)
      - "A Celebration of Rudy Burckhardt" clippings, undated (Box 47, Folder 475)
      - "A Celebration of Rudy Burckhardt" [notebook], undated (Box 47, Folder 476)
      - "Dual Citizenship: The Playful Art and Suicide of Rudy Burckhardt", undated (Box 47, Folder 477)
      - "Notes While Looking at Catalogue" Rudy Burckhardt exhibition, undated (Box 47, Folder 478)
      - Rudy Burckhardt selected photographs, undated (Box 47, Folder 479-480)
      - Rudy Burckhardt's Life and Work: How Wide is Sixth Avenue, undated (Box 47, Folder 481-482)
      - Rudy Burckhardt's Life and Work: How Wide is Sixth Avenue, undated (Box 48, Folder 483)
      - Rackstraw Downes' thank you letter and review to Phillip Lopate, undated (Box 48, Folder 484)
    - The Rug Merchant
      - The Rug Merchant memo notebook, undated (Box 48, Folder 485)
      - The Rug Merchant author's notebooks, undated (Box 48, Folder 486-487)
      - The Rug Merchant chapter annotated drafts, undated (Box 48, Folder 488-491)
      - The Rug Merchant dead matter [excisions] with letter from editor, undated (Box 48, Folder 492)
      - The Rug Merchant dead matter [excisions], undated (Box 49, Folder 493-494)
      - The Rug Merchant final copy, undated (Box 49, Folder 495-497)
      - The Rug Merchant fan letters, undated (Box 49, Folder 498)
      - The Rug Merchant letters and publicity, undated (Box 49, Folder 499)
      - The Rug Merchant book reviews, undated (Box 49, Folder 500-502)
      - Der Teppichhandler draft [The Rug Merchant translation by Lopate], undated (Box 49, Folder 503)
      - The Rug Merchant screenplay by Lopate's student, undated (Box 49, Folder 504)
    - Portrait Inside My Head [originally Essay Love]
      - Earlier versions of essays in new essay books-movies, cities, books, and friends, undated (Box 50, Folder 505-506)
      - Films, books, and cities; drafts of various essays for Essay Love, undated (Box 50, Folder 507-510)
      - Essay Love annotated draft, undated (Box 50, Folder 511-513)
      - Essay Love annotated draft, undated (Box 51, Folder 514)
      - "The Limits of Empathy" and "Duration, or Going Long", undated (Box 51, Folder 515)
      - "Why I Remain a Baseball Fan", undated (Box 51, Folder 516)
      - Essay Love: A Bazaar's Worth of Ruminations on Friends, Family, Books, Movies, Cities, Sex, Politics, Baseball, Religion, and Other Preoccupations, undated (Box 51, Folder 517-519)
    - Portrait of My Body
      - Portrait of My Body copy edited draft, undated (Box 51, Folder 520-523)
    - To Show and To Tell
      - Do Tell: Thinking About Nonfiction original draft, undated (Box 52, Folder 524-526)
      - To Show and To Tell: The Craft of Literary Nonfiction annotated draft, undated (Box 52, Folder 527-529)
      - To Show and To Tell second draft, undated (Box 52, Folder 530)
      - "Imagination, Thin and Thick," first published column in Creative Nonfiction, undated (Box 52, Folder 531)
    - Two Marriages
      - Two Marriages research [notebooks], undated (Box 52, Folder 532)
      - Eleanor, or the Second Marriage [notebooks], undated (Box 52, Folder 533)
      - Eleanor, or the Second Marriage annotated draft, undated (Box 53, Folder 534)
      - "Martial Happiness" draft, undated (Box 53, Folder 535)
      - Two Marriages annotated draft, undated (Box 53, Folder 536-540)
      - Two Marriages master proof, undated (Box 53, Folder 541-543)
      - Two Marriages: A Pair of Novellas clean copy, undated (Box 54, Folder 544-546)
      - Two Marriages clippings, undated (Box 54, Folder 547)
    - Waterfront
      - "Nature and the City" [notebook], undated (Box 54, Folder 548)
      - "The Pen on Foot: The Literature of Walking Around" essay drafts and notes, undated (Box 54, Folder 549)
      - Waterfront: Wanderings and Soundings Along Manhattan's Edge early annotated draft and editor's first cuts [excisions], undated (Box 54, Folder 550-552)
      - Waterfront: Wanderings and Soundings Along Manhattan's Edge early annotated draft and editor's first cuts [excisions], undated (Box 55, Folder 553-555)
      - Waterfront: Wanderings and Soundings Along Manhattan's Edge original copy, latest version, undated (Box 55, Folder 556-560)
      - Waterfront: Wanderings and Soundings Along Manhattan's Edge copy, undated (Box 56, Folder 561-565)
      - Waterfront copy edited final version, undated (Box 56, Folder 566-569)
      - Waterfront copy edited final version, undated (Box 57, Folder 570)
      - Waterfront reviews and publicity, undated (Box 57, Folder 571-576)
    - Translations [by others]
      - Italian translations and correspondence, undated (Box 57, Folder 577)
      - Requests for translations, undated (Box 57, Folder 578)
      - Spanish and Italian translations and correspondence for Rug Merchant and Two Marriages, undated (Box 57, Folder 579)
  - Screenplays
    - General
      - Fiji script, general notes, 1992 (Box 58, Folder 580-581)
      - Heart of Light, an original work by Cynthia Beatt, with Tilda Swinson as Farra, undated (Box 58, Folder 582)
      - Heart of Light, a screenplay by Phillip Lopate based on a story by Cynthia Beatt, 1994 (Box 58, Folder 583)
      - "Taiwan screenplay for Tom Luddy" [American Lost screenplay by Peter Wang and Lopate], 1998 (Box 58, Folder 584-586)
      - "Taiwan screenplay for Tom Luddy" [American Lost screenplay by Peter Wang and Lopate], 1998 (Box 59, Folder 587)
      - Talks with Tilda in Roma transcript [Fiji], undated (Box 58, Folder 588)
      - The Way of Childhood is Hard, a musical play by Phillip Lopate, undated (Box 59, Folder 589)
    - My Guru
      - Guru [composition books], 1991 (Box 59, Folder 590)
      - My Guru and His Disciple notes and correspondence, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 591)
      - My Guru and His Disciple screenplay notes, undated (Box 59, Folder 592)
      - My Guru and His Disciple screenplay by Phillip Lopate, based on Christopher Isherwood's memoir by the same name, first draft, undated (Box 59, Folder 593-594)
      - My Guru and His Disciple screenplay by Phillip Lopate, based on Christopher Isherwood's memoir by the same name, first draft, undated (Box 60, Folder 595-596)
      - My Guru and His Disciple screenplay first draft transcript, undated (Box 60, Folder 597-598)
      - My Guru and His Disciple screenplay, earlier version, undated (Box 60, Folder 599)
      - My Guru and His Disciple screenplay, bound copy, undated (Box 60, Folder 600)
      - My Guru and His Disciple partial screenplay, undated (Box 60, Folder 601)
    - Waif [based on Tanizaki's Naomi]
      - My screenplay based on Tanizaki's Naomi, 1994 (Box 60, Folder 602)
      - Waif, a screenplay by Phillip Lopate, undated (Box 61, Folder 603-604)
      - Waif, a screenplay by Phillip Lopate and Lorenzo Semple, Jr., undated (Box 61, Folder 605-607)
  - Early works
    - Early stories
      - Early stories, general, undated (Box 61, Folder 608)
      - "Billy Among the Beggars", undated (Box 61, Folder 609)
      - "Bungalow on Horseshoe Pond" annotated draft, undated (Box 61, Folder 610-612)
      - "Bungalow on Horseshoe Pond" annotated draft, undated (Box 62, Folder 613-614)
      - "To the 'Reader' and Pink Walls" annotated draft, undated (Box 62, Folder 615)
    - College papers
      - Guide to Tuolumne Meadows Trails, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 616)
      - College and early papers and writings, general, circa 1962-circa 1966 (Box 62, Folder 617-621)
      - College and early papers and writings, general, circa 1962-circa 1966 (Box 63, Folder 622)
      - [Notebook], 1968 (Box 63, Folder 623)
      - Ken (the John Man) [composition book], undated (Box 63, Folder 624-625)
      - Brookline-Aunt Frances and Uncle George [notebook], undated (Box 63, Folder 626)
      - Color of Dreams [steno notebook], undated (Box 63, Folder 627)
      - [Loose notes], undated (Box 63, Folder 628)
      - Disappointment [University of Houston notebook], undated (Box 63, Folder 629)
    - Lopate's first novel Best Friends
      - Confrontations with Best Friends annotated typescript, undated (Box 64, Folder 630-633)
      - Best Friends typed copy, undated (Box 64, Folder 634-638)
  - Printed materials
    - Anchor Essay Annual, Best of 1998 advance uncorrected proof (Box 65, Folder 639)
    - In Coyoacan, 1971 (Box 65, Folder 640)
    - Journal of a Living Experiment, 1979 (Box 65, Folder 641)
    - Teachers Guide to the Art of the Personal Essay, 1994 (Box 65, Folder 642)
- Personal Papers, 1951–2000; 3; 4 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
  This series primarily consists of Lopate's personal diaries and journals, memo books, and notebooks. Also present are interviews and news clippings about Lopate, dating from 1951 to 2000, which cover his academic and literary career. Diaries kept while he was a student are organized by year or semester. Later diaries span his early career as a teacher and writer, and some chronicle his travels to Russia, Israel, and other countries in the Middle East.
  Organized into two subseries: Diaries and journals, and Interviews and clippings about Phillip Lopate. Arranged chronologically.
  - Diaries and journals
    - 1961 on [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 643)
    - 1966 on [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 644)
    - 1969 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 645)
    - 1975 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 646)
    - 1975 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 647)
    - Spring-Summer 1976 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 648)
    - Begun June 7, 1977 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 649)
    - Begun February 8, 1978 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 650)
    - 1979 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 651)
    - 1980 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 652)
    - 1980 [diary] (Box 66, Folder 653)
    - Houston Diary begun August 17, 1980 (Box 66, Folder 654)
    - 1981 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 655)
    - Began June 1981 [record book] (Box 66, Folder 656)
    - Daily Reminder 1981 [date book] (Box 66, Folder 657)
    - 1982 [date book] (Box 66, Folder 658)
    - Begun February 7, 1982 [record book] (Box 66, Folder 659)
    - 1983 [address book] (Box 66, Folder 660)
    - Begun July 14, 1983 [record book] (Box 66, Folder 661)
    - 1984 [date book] (Box 66, Folder 662)
    - 1984 [notebook] (Box 66, Folder 663)
    - November 7, 1984 longer published version [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 664)
    - 1985 [date book] (Box 67, Folder 665)
    - Begun September 9, 1985 [record book] (Box 67, Folder 666)
    - [Brown date book], 1986 (Box 67, Folder 667)
    - Begun July 23, 1986 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 668)
    - [Date book], 1987 (Box 67, Folder 669)
    - 1988 Middle East Visa [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 670)
    - Phillip Lopate [date book], 1988 (Box 67, Folder 671)
    - Begun in Houston, March 8, 1988 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 672)
    - Berlin notes 1989 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 673)
    - [Address book], 1990 (Box 67, Folder 674)
    - Manhattan Diary 1981 [notebook], 1991 (Box 67, Folder 675)
    - [Date book], 1992 (Box 67, Folder 676)
    - Hofstra University [planner], 1994 (Box 67, Folder 677)
    - Lily Pad, begun September 17, 1994 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 678)
    - [Partial date book section], September 1993-January 1994 (Box 67, Folder 679)
    - Begun October 10, 1995 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 680)
    - 1996 Diary (Box 67, Folder 681)
    - Started April 13, 2000 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 682)
    - Began September 28, 2000 [notebook] (Box 67, Folder 683)
    - Addresses, undated (Box 67, Folder 684)
    - [Address book], undated (Box 67, Folder 685)
    - [Journal], undated (Box 67, Folder 686)
    - [Notebook], undated (Box 67, Folder 687)
    - [Notebook], undated (Box 67, Folder 688)
    - Brooklyn Book Festival [notebook], undated (Box 67, Folder 689)
    - "The European Story" [notebook], undated (Box 68, Folder 690)
    - [Notebook], undated (Box 68, Folder 691)
    - Hofstra [exam book], undated (Box 68, Folder 692)
    - The Isherwood Movie [notebook], undated (Box 68, Folder 693)
    - Israel diaries, undated (Box 68, Folder 694)
    - Miami Dade College [spiral notebook], undated (Box 68, Folder 695)
    - St. Petersburg, Russia [diary], undated (Box 68, Folder 696)
    - Trip to Russia [diary], undated (Box 68, Folder 697)
    - Writing Life in a Book [diary], undated (Box 68, Folder 698)
    - [Diary], undated (Box 69, Folder 699)
  - Interviews and clippings about Phillip Lopate
    - Eastern District High School, Columbia clippings, correspondence, and certificates, circa 1957-circa 1965 (Box 70, Folder 700-701)
    - Columbia Spectator clippings, circa 1960-circa 1963 (Box 70, Folder 702-704)
    - Individual poems and short prose, clipped, circa 1975-1979 (Box 70, Folder 705)
    - Uncategorized clippings, circa 1975-circa 1988 (Box 70, Folder 706)
    - Lists of publications and reviews, clippings, circa 1975-circa 1998 (Box 70, Folder 707)
    - Interviews with Phillip Lopate, circa 1975-circa 2007 (Box 70, Folder 708)
    - Interviews with Phillip Lopate, circa 1975-circa 2007 (Box 71, Folder 709-715)
    - Clippings about me, circa 1976-circa 2004 (Box 71, Folder 716)
    - Recommendations and applications for fellowships, professorships, circa 1979-circa 1996 (Box 71, Folder 717)
    - Recommendations and applications for fellowships, professorships, circa 1979-circa 1996 (Box 72, Folder 718)
    - Brief mentions in the press, circa 2008-circa 2015 (Box 72, Folder 719)
    - Introductions, organizations, "Best 18 Essays" and "Best 25 Books", 2013 (Box 72, Folder 720)
- Teaching Materials, 1968–1975; 4; 2.25 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
  This series consists of Lopate's correspondence with other educators and students, student evaluations of courses he taught at Bennington College, Lopate's Hofstra University teaching diaries, comics drawn by children at Public School 75 in Manhattan, New York, and an edition of Black Cat, a comic book published by the PS 75 Comics Group under the guidance of Lopate and other teachers.